Mss.Rec.16 Mss.Rec.16
American Philosophical Society
Cherokee materials gathered...on the Cherokee reservation at Cherokee, N.C.
1951-1952
Mss.Rec.16
American Philosophical Society
9.0 Reel(s)
Includes folkloric stories, conversation (concerning religion, sons in the military, letters from friends), and a variety of elicitations to test freedom of word order between two generations of speakers, classificatory verbs, word pairs with contrast of vowel length and stress, verb affixes and suffixes, and immediate and regular imperative verbs. Recorded at the Cherokee Indian Reservation, North Carolina from 1951-1952.
9 sound tape reels (4 hr., 26 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in.
Conseen, Annie Oocumma
Reyburn, William D.
Youngdeer, Jess
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by William Reyburn in 1952. This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Related Archival Materials
Transcriptions and translations accompanying this recording are available in the Franz Boas Collection of Materials for American Linguistics (Mss.497.3.B63c I2.3, pt. 3).
Cherokee Indians--Folklore; Cherokee language; Military service, Voluntary--United States; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Minimal word pairs with contrast of vowel length and stress, 1951-09-10; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:59; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.
    Scope and Contents note
    Recorded as part of research funded by an APS Phillips Fund grant.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Cherokee Indian Reservation (N.C.); Cherokee language; Cherokee language--Phonology
  - Race of the Deer and the Four Turtles, 1951-09-10; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:51; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.
    Cherokee Indian Reservation (N.C.); Cherokee Indians--Folklore; Deer--Folklore; Turtles--Folklore
  - Bear and Rabbit Invitation to Eat, 1951-09-10; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:08; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.
    Bears--Folklore; Cherokee Indian Reservation (N.C.); Cherokee Indians--Folklore; Rabbits--Folklore
  - Grammatical elicitations, 1951-07-10; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:39; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.
    Possessive pronomial suffixes; Verb stems and affixes; Word order permutations. Recorded as part of research funded by an APS Phillips Fund grant.
    Cherokee Indian Reservation (N.C.); Cherokee language; Cherokee language--Morphology; Cherokee language--Syntax; Cherokee language--Verbs
  - Contrasting pairs of words with 1st and 3rd sg. pronomials with H.; Classificatory verbs, 1951-07-20; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:33:26; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.
    "Many contrasting pairs of 1st & 3rd persons employing non 1st person H.; List of classifactory verbs expressing long, round flexible and liquid properties." Recorded as part of research funded by an APS Phillips Fund grant.
    Cherokee Indian Reservation (N.C.); Cherokee language--Morphology; Cherokee language--Syntax; Cherokee language--Verbs
  - Prayer before meal with full half-hour of uninterrupted conversation while eating breakfast, 1951-08-06; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:39; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.; Youngdeer, Jess
    "This reel is a recording of the conversation between Jess Youngdeer and Annie Conseen at the breakfast table of the latter. Aug 6, 1951. Reel begins with the saying of grace by A. Conseen. The natural conversation that follows is a discussion of their common interests, covering such subjects as religion, sons in the service, letters from friends, note the greater contour risings in the speech of A. Conseen." Includes brief conversation in Englsh. Recorded as part of research funded by an APS Phillips Fund grant.
    Cherokee Indian Reservation (N.C.); Cherokee language; Letter writing; Military service, Voluntary--United States; Prayers; Religion
  - Series of utterances designed to test freedom of word order between two generations of speakers, 1952-01-15; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:18; Arch, Sarah; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.; Welch, Enoch; Welch, Woodrow
    "This reel is a group informant response designed to test the freedom of word order in Cherokee utterances.... Sentences allowing complete permutations of word order." Recorded as part of research funded by an APS Phillips Fund grant.
    Cherokee Indian Reservation (N.C.); Cherokee language; Cherokee language--Syntax; Historical linguistics
  - Verb paradigms to indicate thematic elements and stem classes, 1951-11-10; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:42; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.
    "Verb paradigms of approximately 50 verbs. This includes pronomial variations and verb stem suffixes also provides stems indicating majority of verb stem classes." Recorded as part of research funded by an APS Phillips Fund grant.
  - Verb stems with various affixes, 1952-01-25; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:47; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.
    "This material includes approximately 100 verb stems with affix variations. These verb stems are used as part of a looser corpus upon which the verb stem classification is based." Recorded as part of research funded by an APS Phillips Fund grant.
  - Verbs exhibiting the suffix whose range of meaning is immediate imperative, recent past and conditional, 1952-01-30; 08-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:50; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.
    "Imperative verb suffixes. Immediate imperative; Regular imperative." Recorded as part of research funded by an APS Phillips Fund grant.
  - Verb suffixes and word order, 1952-02-05; 09-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:28:43; Conseen, Annie Oocumma; Reyburn, William D.
    "Verb suffixes giving relative order or suffixes. Suffix 'repeated action' with morphological suffixes following. Syntactic order of words in sentence." Recorded as part of research funded by an APS Phillips Fund grant.